[Music]
etc etc etc something less than a
masterpiece that fugue had you heard it before?
- Never - Would you be willing to
hear any more of it? there's quite a bit
more where that came from - I ... hope I can
be excused but I think I could do without it.
- Really? I... I think it has great
charm, charm out of all proportion to its craft actually....
- yeah, but to me it sounds
more like a fugue um by Haendel perhaps than by Bach
- Oh well that's quite true all
those very self-confident Triads
supporting very insecure sequences that is quite haendily you're quite right
but that's Bach, you know, in the early years when he caught on to a phrase that he
really liked he just kept devaluating the
currency using it again and again as as equence, he just coined in and couldn't stop, I mean
I suspect, to be honest, that, fond as
I am of it, and I read?? am, that,
had it not been for the fact that we see him writing a rather special subject
- b a c h? - well yeah, German speaking keyboard say
b a c h our local variety says b flat a c b natural,
which spoils the fun, but, had
it not been for the fact that on German
speaking keyboard you can make him write a fugue subject on his own name,
I think this piece might well have languished in more obscurity than it's found already
but having said that, I... I still think it
is a very very charming piece and a lot
better than some of the other
early fugues that he wrote in in fact
- Are you thinking of the... the fugues from the... toccatas for instance? - the toccatas and
some of the early organ works too uh,
where he gets involved in
exactly the same kind of sequential hangups that he does here you know... it's it's not... we have this ...
we have this happy idea, that, because Bach turned out, arguably, to be
the greatest craftsman of all time, that
he started out that way, that he produced
masterpieces in his play pen and he did not; he was not even a very fast (starter?)
as a as a fugue writer you know what he had
right from the earliest days it seems
was the ability to write music of
incredible um intensity and and (pathos?), the kind of recitative that you get in the
toccatas, even the earliest ones could
virtually have gone into the Matthew
passion and and you know I mean they're
extraordinary things but he did not have
the ability to integrate that intensity
with a regal Fugal craft until he was I
think close to 40 you know - well, is there
an example of integration that you could
give us now? - How about the um e major fugue
from the second volume of the Well Tempered Clavier...
[Music]
You know it isn't exactly the
world's most original thought but um
what a coral piece this would have made...
- Absolutely every line seems to be conceived
vocally - Yeah yeah and maybe because he
wasn't trying to cater to an instrument
in any way there's a sense that there
isn't a wasted note there isn't an
artificial a superficial note, everything
is material, to the material, everything
absolutely grows out of the original
subject, you know, the original six notes
which started it all...
[Music]
even the first counter theme does
because that counter theme
[Music]
is just a transposition of the subject...
to... with a little bit of
ornamentation and then after he gets
through the exposition what I just
played the um exposition where every
voice has its say once he starts into
the first of those wonderfully compact
uh convoluted - in the best sense of the
word - stretto overlaps
[Music]
Only in this one the counter theme gets
its own stretto as well - So that the the
two ideas seem to develop in tandem?
- Exactly and in tandem, or otherwise, they
move but one can't say they modulate
together they sort of um bump into the
uh the submediant Key C sharp minor - lastly - and
when he gets there he does something
rather cute: he takes the original
subject and the original answer, starting
on the notes which they did start on E
and B, respectively, and transforms them,
reharmonizes them um finds a way of
giving them a sort of tonal (visit / visa?) to pass
through C sharp minor
- As they're doing so, they're
associatiated in that same key with a new
counter subject compete with its own
counter subject... - that's true ...
well I said yes, that's true, and
it's not quite true because in a way um
what this is is a kind of wild
permutation of the very first motive
with which in the second bar he
accompanies the answer...
so, farfetched as it may seem, even
that doesn't doesn't go to waste entirely
[Music]
Then, they leave the orbit of C sharp minor, if
they were ever in fact in it, and move to
the same extent that they were in C sharp
toward F sharp minor
in wich key he does something very nice: he
takes the theme, deprives it of the one
expressive interval it has, the the minor
third, and fills it in, as one would would
sing it in a scale
[Music]
then makes the alto comment on
that also sort of filling in the pattern
except that in the alto he starts to
play around with the modes and goes up
one way
and comes back down another
then he adds a new counter theme
in the base...
also based on the original idea of...
and also expanding it to the
interval of a fifth
and then puts that into a um a
canon in the tenor just in case anybody
missed the point
[Music]
Then they leave F sharp minor by the
same submediant route by C sharp minor
...exit...
then you get another one of those
glorious stretto um occasions as as in
the second sentence of the piece... then
he does something very very interesting
after forgive me after after that stretto,
for the first time, he introduces six
diatonic notes in a row which doesn't seem
like doing anything very special...
but up to (land?), every motive that
he's used has either been delineated by
a fourth... as in ... or on a fifth as in the
case of the counter subjects...
he suddenly adds six notes
successively
...then in Canon, seven...
[Music]
as though to sort of celebrate the
ending which seems to be close by
except it isn't that close he's gotta
back off once more and he backs into
the submediant key which he hasn't
visited before, G sharp minor
and from that he goes to a coda which
begins with the only diatonic scale in the
entire piece, scale of e major, uh so we
have first the six note thing the seven
note extension the eight note extension
and it's rudimentary material but it
makes for one of the most gloriously
fulfilled coders he ever wrote I think
- Well what about playing the the whole
fugue now? - Yeah okay I think I should and
um one Masterpiece coming up
[Music]
as I said a masterpiece - Yeah for the
moment at least it's for me the my
favorite in all music - Oh I know that
feeling. I often wondered if it mightn't
have been um Schoenberg's, you know, Schoenberg's favorite
piece, you know, it exemplifies everything
that he believed in, he had that theory
that he called uh developing variation
where every note and every bar and every
phrase and every sentence and every
paragraph had to be seen to belong to
that organism and to no other and I
can't think of any piece that
exemplifies that in the way that this
does - I agree but don't you think that
that E major Fugue is a very special
case? It is a vocal composition, I mean,
like a vocal composition - Oh, certainly, it's a
it's a 16th century (???) with a with a
(key signature?) it has that very disciplined
very severe very very Renaissance like
attitude toward counterpoint - Yeah but
there are many great fugues which don't
subscribe to those particular
disciplines so rigidly um, which do grow
of an instrumental approach, that doesn't
make them less worthy as - Oh no no no, of
course not, um well, for example the the
first uh the first three-part invention
the first symphonia you know ...
that's based on a subject that
you would not be likely to sing I guess
you could ... well not no you couldn't not
very easily and it could only be an
instrumental approach but I certainly
wouldn't say it's it's any the less
worthy for that reason
[Music]
you know in its own way that little symphonia
is (everybody / equally as??) concentrated as the E major
fugue - Certainly is - (Of course??) the fugue
really was a combination of Renaissance
ideas about imitation and voice leading
and so on the kind of ideas that were in
that e major fugue and of baroque ideas
of key order and key relationship about
the uses of the diatonic scale and the
pecking order of it of its cords and so
on - Well the the kind of harmonic
patterns that made that symphonia hold
together - Yeah, exactly, all of the
imitative devices that we know in fugue
like canon and inversion and
augmentation and diminution all that
sort of thing all of the mathematical
processes were in place in the
Renaissance you know and all were used
with great sophistication in the 16th
century really but the fugue in order to
be independent, in order to stand own
feet, needed something else and I think
that something else was was tonality, it
really is a celebration of the tonal
system of the peculiar stresses and
strains and pulls and pushes and
magnetic attractions of one cord for
another - Yeah but you're not saying that
the fugue for instance in Bach's time depends
upon tonality is in the way that that
the Sonata (or Libero??) does in Beethoven style? - No no
no because the the pecking order there
is really quite different um I think
however that there is nothing in the
nature of fugue that would want to
demand what Beethoven would demand of
the relationship between a a tonic and a
dominant or a tonic and a mediant for
his first and second themes Bach would have no
use for that particular kind of tonic
mediant tonic dominant relationship you
know but that's a plus that's a great
plus in a way, because the fugue then is
not locked
into a have-to-concept there is no
specific modulatory plan that to which
it has to conform the composer can use
as much or as little modulation as he
wants um and he can present a whole
series of, as Schoenberg would have said,
developing variations of the material in
different keys - you well that Bach did
in the in the e major fugue - yeah but there
there was a kind of well I say a kind of
gradual inevitable darwinian evolution
of the material which is very very
marvelous in its existential way but it
isn't in quotation marks "modern" in Bach's
time and there is a a marvelous example
of
a "modern" Fugue in the um B flat minor
you know from book two - the...
[Music]
the you know - that piece is of a totally
different order than the um than the E
major, the theme appears as we sung it
more or less and then at the end of the
exposition uh in in Canon for the first time
[Music]
...and so on. Then later on in inversion...
then an inverted Cannon and so on and
every time he changes the process, every
time he looks at it from a different
angle, he positions it in a different key
to show that angle, even though the first
statements of those processes may very
well be the tonic for example at the end
of the exposition as I kind of wrap up
the exposition he does put it into the
cannon for the first time
[Music]
then he modulates very subtly...
modulates to the mediant and
produces this absolutely enchanted
version in Canon
[Music]
you know and he's not using
tonality though even by doing that by
relating the tonic and and the mediant he's
not using tonality as even many
contemporary, Scarlatti say, used it -
To use a fashionable word Bach was not a
minimalist you know he wasn't concerned
about staying put in one key but the
dramatic effects of doing that. He wasn't
concerned about trying to balance
so many minutes of key x with so many
minutes of key y uh for the second theme
or whatever... He's really not terribly
concerned ever
about exploiting the whole process of
time itself as a compositional element
in the way that later composers, the
classical composers, particularity where.
I mean when Bach juxtaposes a tonic and
a mediant as he did there
it's a totally different kind of
juxtoposition of keys than this... tonic
[Music]
juxtaposed with this mediant
... you know. Bach, unlike Beethoven,
uses all those keys as you might do
stops on an organ they give them ideas
they give them colors they give them
registrations for the incredible
incredible motivic workings out that are
taking place in this rather incredible fugue
[Music]
you know one almost has to coin some
other word than modulation for what Bach
does in a fugue like that it it it's it's
not modulation just it it's it's key
perception or something like that he he
perceives the qualities inherent in
every every key he passes through in in
a spooky way it's it's marvelous - Yeah
absolutely it's not just a an amazing um
contrapunctal tour-de-force it's also an amazing
harmonic conception - Harmonic, absolutely,
absolutely, yeah, indeed - You know Glenn um
I can't help noticing that in all our
discussion you've not once mentioned the
word Prelude - The word Prelude you say?
well no it's a it's a splendid word, how
many times would you like me to mention
it? - Well, if you're talking about the Welltempered
Clavier, what about just as many
times as the word fugue? - Well I tell you I
personally think that a lot of the
fugues in the Welltempered Clavier are better
off without their attending preludes and
vice versa - Oh come on that's that really (a personal taste??)
- There's no accounting for taste, Bruno, I
I I do though I I think that there are
great preludes there are fantastic
pieces I didn't mean that to sound
patronizing they're incredible preludes
marvelous preludes but they very often
especially the good ones the really good
ones are the ones that bother me the
most because very often they don't match
their fugues. I can't give you any better
example of that than the Prelude that
prefaces that incredible e major thing
that we talked about before, you know, in
front of um a magnificent Neo
renaissance edifice what does he put? He
puts a gentle lovely charming
rococo
bewigged 18th century triosonata, makes no sense
[Music]
You know it's a wonderful piece
but I can't see for the life of me what
it's got to do with that that ...
... an incredible fugue. It's as if the
two movements are 100 years apart
technically and and emotionally as if
they just belong to a a different world
altogether, different way of looking at
the world altogether - Yeah but are there
no preludes and fugues that in your view um
do add up to something more than the sum of
their parts? - Well I don't know about more
than the some of their parts I think
there are some that seem to have (sprung??)
spontaneously from the same trade (of
impulse, a few ???). - Yeah I think you ow us at
least one of those? - At least one. Well I
think I would vote for the a major from
again from book two of the Welltempered
Clavier. I think that one really is all of
the piece all of a very gentle lyrical
quietly optimistic, utterly charming piece
[Music]
That works that perlude and that fugue
belong together. - Yes, they absolutely
do. Glenn, what is it that gave the fugue
such a major role in bar creative life?
And what is it with that matter that
keeps it going or kept it going to the
point that one gets polytonal fugues and atonal
fugues 12 tone fugues and even fugue at the
end of symphonies for most romantic
composers (great choruses??) I mean what
what is it that accounts for that
continuing fascination for the fugue? - Well
I suppose there many reasons really
I think perhaps there is one that is
predominant and it is really very
difficult to define. I think it has
something to do with a very special need
that certain types of artists exhibit,
the need to prove that what they do is is um
is valid that is not achieved by random
selection, that every moment flows
logically from from the moment before to
the moment after. It's not confined to
musicians, that need, but maybe because
music itself is so so unprovable so
improbable you know one might almost say
musicians somehow seem to exhibit it
more prominently than some other types
of artists ... It's very difficult at times
with certain kinds of music particularly
to say WHY something strikes one as
appropriate or or inappropriate. You know,
you and I have often argued about middle
period Beethoven, and I do not intend to
reopen that argument again... - I'm certainly
glad to hear that. - No no no I wouldn't
dream with that, I've given that up
as a lost cause. I don't really ever
expect to persuade you of the pomposity
of the Fifth Symphony or the banality of
the violin conerto with the empty rhetoric
of the (... sonata ???) no I I I would not think
preopening at argument as I say.
And in fact, when you come right down to it,
there is no way to to argue as I think we
found from frustrating past experience I
mean I can say to you this is a tiresome idea...
...and I would say to you right away, I mean,
in the context this is a (moment??)... - In the
context, you see, you would have to say
that I'm sure you would. But
notwithstanding our argument, Beethoven, as
we all know, had a very special
temperament, as, in those middle years,
when he wrote that - junk - , he had absolute
confidence that what he did was valid
just because he did it you know. It's a
great gift, I'm not arguing against
intuitional creativity or anything like
that there. I'm simply saying that most,
most composers don't have that... gift, they
don't have that audacity, they don't have
the nerve to try and get away with...
something as silly as that, really. They
can't talk themselves into it, much less
expect that the listener is going to
accept what they do is by a leap of
faith or something. You know most
composers are just much more fragile
than than was Bethoven. I mean, why do you
think Richard Strauss wrote all those
incredible tone poems of his, in which
every thematic idea, every modulation had
to be accounted for by a literary
parallel of some kind. I think he did it,
I think he erected all those
programmatic scaffolds to convince
himself, really, that everything he did
had an architectural reason, that there
was nothing that was improvisatory in
terms of the structure, everything
belonged. And he did it so well as you
can take down those scaffoldings you can
play until (all spel??) for a child who's
never even heard the term program music
and get a very positive and purely
musical reaction, you know, which is the
way it should be.
Well I think, in a funny way, contrapunctal forms,
fugues and cannons and so on, are like
that. You know, either a cannon works or
it does not work, either it fulfills the
particular thou-shalts and thou-shalt-nots
of the canon form or or it doesn't do
that. And in the same way, the fugue is a
process which is about process, really. It
concentrates on process and one is not
likely in a fugue to be seduced by the
momentary um attraction or or
distraction of a particular idea. I mean,
you can say to me um I I I think that
the ninth fugue of The Art Of Fugue is a rather
intrusive and virtuosic subject.
[Music]
And if you did say that, I really
wouldn't disagree with you, to tell you
the truth. But I would say to you, well, no
matter, it it works it works as a subject
in its own exposition and it works as a
countertheme, it mates perfectly well
with the with the main theme of The Art Of Fugue.
[Music]
So, in a way that we will never be
able to find agreement about the second
theme of Beethoven's Emperor Concerto, we could
say, well okay, it's a theme of no
distinction whatsoever but it does have
an ongoing relationship with the
totality of this particular structure,
with the totality of The Art Of Fugue, you know.
- Well you're mentioning The Art Of Fugue,
which you're going to play three fugues in
a moment. - Yes, the second, the fourth and
the the 15th. - Do you share the general
view that this is the combination of all
Bach's fugue writing? - Yes, I do, but not
specifically because of its scope and
scale and technical wizardry and all
that sort of thing, not just because one
one theme generates 15 fugues and four
cannons, amazing as that is, there are
moments in The Art Of Fugue that are much
more valuable than its virtuosity. I
think, moments that, for me, absolutely
surpass everything else that Bach
wrote. I I really can't think of any
music that moved me more deeply than
than that last fugue, you know - the The
Unfinished one - the unfinished Fugue. And not just
because of all the emotional
associations that we inevitably bring to
it, not just because we know that, he died
leaving it incomplete, leaving it
literally in the middle of a bar, already
enormously long as it was. It really is
because that final fugue has a sense of
peace, a devotional quality that I think,
even for barock, is is really
overwhelming. The interesting thing about
that that final fugue, and to some extent
about all of The Art Of Fugue, is, that, in it, he
literally turns his back on every
tendency abroad in the musical world of
his time. - Well, by the time he wrote it
fugues were very unpopular. - Oh well, hugely
unpopular. Uh, and fugal adventures of this
size and tenacity were simply unheard of,
they had no place at all in the 18th
century scheme of things. Fugues were out
and menuettes were in, I guess, but more
than that, Bach actually, I think quite
deliberately, changes his harmonic style
in this work. There is nothing in The
Art Of Fugue remotely like the clear-cut
modulations of that B flat minor fugue
for example or the e major fugue, that we
talked about a few moments ago, or almost
any of the earlier fugues really. Instead, he
reaches back at least 100 years and bores a
type of counterpoint and a concept of
key association from the from the north
German, the Flemish composers of the of
the early Baroque this kind of texture...
you know it allows them to write
tonally, but without any of the
(technicolor??) trappings of tonality. For me,
these pieces contain an endless range of
gray tints. I mean as a compliment.
because I love gray. Schweitzer as a
matter of fact had some marvelous things
to say. He said it was a still and serious
world, deserted and rigid, without color
and without light and without motion and
so on. He he was talking about the first
fugue, I think, specifically, but that pretty
well sums up my feeling about the last
one too, I must say. But the other side of
the coin is that Bach introduces into
The Art Of Fugue a degree of chromaticism
that, in many respects, reaches out, I
think, at least until the time of Wagner,
at least for 100 years beyond his own
time. There's nothing remotely like it in
in between really and it's very similar
to to wagnerian and post wagnerian
chromaticism in that it constantly
reaches farther and farther and father.
It never it never modulates in the
conventional sense, it never comes to
rest in any one key, you know, but it
leaves the extraordinary impression of
an infinitely expanding Universe... you know, moments like this,
which could almost have been written by
early Schoenberg, you know...
But of course, in this last fugue, he
also develops three separate subjects,
the last of which is the the one on his
own name - that's right, and there could
not be a more a more striking more
amazing contrast between the way he uses
those four notes here and the way he
used them at the beginning of the fugue
that I played at the top of the program.
I mean, here, all of the extroversion, all
of the superfluous excitement, has gone.
You know he's he's literally signing his
name to what what he obviously knew
would be the word that summed up his
life. And since that life was one in
which he moved farther and farther outside
of the orbit of expectations, that the
world um thrust upon him, in all of his
work, even in those moments of great
vigor and great energy and so on, he he
manages to telescope that incredible
journey in in really the most
extraordinary way.